A Finding Aid to the Anthony Palumbo Papers, 1947-2008, bulk 1968-2008, in the Archives of American Art AAA.paluanth
Archives of American Art
Anthony Palumbo papers
bulk 1968-2008
1947-2008
AAA.paluanth
Archives of American Art
0.6 Linear feet
The papers of New York painter and art instructor Anthony Palumbo measure 0.6 linear feet and date from 1947 to 2008, with the bulk of materials dating from 1968 to 2008. The collection documents Palumbo's work through his writings and drawings mostly used as teaching materials. Also found are exhibition catalogs, clippings, and photographs of his work.
Palumbo, Anthony
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The papers were donated to the Archives of American Art in 2013 by Phyllis Tracy Malinow (Phyllis Malinow Palumbo), widow of Palumbo.
Conditions Governing Access note
The Anthony Palumbo papers are owned by the Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution. Literary rights as possessed by the donor have been dedicated to public use for research, study, and scholarship. The collection is subject to all copyright laws.
Biographical/Historical note
Anthony Palumbo (1922-2008) was a painter and instructor at the Art Students League of New York. Born in Italy, Palumbo immigrated to the United States in 1929. During the Depression he attended art classes in New Jersey and apprenticed with well-known W.P.A. artists. In the army during World War II, Palumbo served as a radio technician and produced cartoons on GI life for Army publications.
Palumbo then studied at the Art Students League of New York and the New School for Social Research with artists such as Reginald Marsh and Stuart Davis. He also studied privately with Hans Hofmann and Burne Hogarth, working as a cartoonist to sustain his fine artwork. His cartoons were published in the Chicago Tribune, The Philadelphia Inquirer and Collier's magazine. In the 1950s he traveled to Mexico, where he assisted muralist Rufino Tamayo. Returning to New York, he established a studio and continued to paint until 1960 when he lost his artwork in a catastrophic studio fire. That same year Palumbo was included in the Whitney Museum's annual presentation of contemporary art.
The next years were difficult for Palumbo, but in 1968 he started teaching at the Art Students League of New York, where he remained a highly regarded and well liked teacher until his death at age 85.
Palumbo was married to Phyllis Malinow, also an artist.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of New York painter and art instructor Anthony Palumbo measure 0.6 linear feet and date from 1947 to 2008, with the bulk of materials dating from 1968 to 2008. The collection documents Palumbo's work through his writings and drawings mostly used as teaching materials. Also found are exhibition catalogs, clippings, and photographs of his work.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original materials requires an appointment.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged in 5 series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 2002-2008 (Box 1; 1 folder)
Series 2: Writings, 1947-2008 (Box 1; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 3: Printed Material, circa 1965-2008 (Box 1; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 4: Artwork and Sketchbook, 1947-2008 (Box 1, OV 2; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 5: Photographs, circa 1965-2008 (Box 1, OV 3; 0.8 linear feet)
Art teachers--New York (State)--New York; Art--Study and teaching; Drawings; Painters--New York (State)--New York; Photographs
- Biographical Material, 2002-2008; Series 1; 1 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical material contains a draft personal essay probably by Palumbo, an obituary clipping, a memento folder given out at his memorial service at The Art Students League of New York, a DVD of this service, and an undated interview with Palumbo by Ira Goldberg. There also are hand written notes which appear to be by Palumbo, noting important events of his life.
  - Biographical Material, 2002-2008; Includes 1 videodisc (DVD) (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Writings, circa 1965-2008; Series 2; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  There are six pocket sized notebooks, which consist of thoughts about art and teaching, loose sheets, and some tracing paper drawings.
  - Notebooks and Notes, circa 1965-2008 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
  - Lists, Notes and Drawings, circa 1965-2008 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Printed Material, 1947-2008; Series 3; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  Printed material includes photocopies of cartoons probably by Palumbo and some clippings relating to his fine artwork; a book by Jon Gngany, TV art instructor, You Are an Artist, autographed by Gnagny with the inscription" …best pal…who did most of the work on the book;" an unpublished bound writing by Palumbo entitled "Figure Drawing Through Easily Recognizable Symbols;" a radio & telegraphic schematic; a poster showing artist-student relationships and influences; and 2 exhibition catalogs, one of a Palumbo retrospective in 2002 and the other from the Selby Gallery at Ringling College of Art and Design in Sarasota, Florida.
  - Printed Material, 1947-2008 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Artwork and Sketchbook, 1947-2008; Series 4; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1, OV 2
  Artwork consists of a small sketch book with 4 drawings or sketches in graphite and crayon. Also found are a few oversized graphite drawings and colored photographic reproductions of brightly colored compositions.
  - Sketchbook, 1947-2008 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Artwork, 1947-2008; Oversized material housed in OV 2 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Oversize Artwork from Box 1, Folder 7, 1947-2008 (Box OV 2)
- Photographs, circa 1965-2008; Series 5; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1, OV 3
  There are two black and white snapshots of Palumbo at an event and four photocopied photographs of him in his studio teaching. The remaining photographs are of drawings and diagrams of the figure with notes, also probably used for classroom teaching. Also found are a few color snapshots and digital prints of paintings.
  - Palumbo, circa 1970-2008 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Figure Study Teaching Material, circa 1965-2008 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Figure Studies, Painting, and Cartoons, circa 1965-2008; Oversized material housed in OV 3 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Oversize Photographs of Artwork from Box 1, Folder 10, circa 1965-2008 (Box OV 3)